<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The life of Captain James Whitney containing his most remarkable robberies and other adventures, &amp;c., continued to his execution near Smithfield Bars, the first of February, 1692/3.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1693</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 80 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A48412</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L2025A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R4823</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12979507</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12979507</idno>
            <idno type="VID">96167</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A48412)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 96167)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 719:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The life of Captain James Whitney containing his most remarkable robberies and other adventures, &amp;c., continued to his execution near Smithfield Bars, the first of February, 1692/3.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for A.R. ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1693]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: p. 30.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Whitney, James, d. 1693.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:96167:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:96167:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE LIFE Of Captain James Whitney.</p>
            <p>Containing, his Moſt Remarkable Robberies And other Adventures, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>CONTINUED To his Execution near <hi>Smithfield</hi> Bars the firſt of <hi>February</hi> 1692/3.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Aude aliquid brevibus Gyaris &amp; carcere dignum</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Si vis eſſe aliquid.—</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>A. R.</hi> near <hi>Temple-Bar.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:96167:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:96167:2"/>
            <head>MEMOIRS OF Capt. James Whitney, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>TO Commence our Hiſtory from the very Birth of our <hi>Hero,</hi> the Subject of our preſent Treatiſe, he deſcended from very bumble Parentage, being born near <hi>Hitchin:</hi> About the Age of 14 he was put Apprentice to a <hi>Butcher</hi> at <hi>Cheſſon,</hi> in <hi>Hertfordſhire;</hi> but before he had half ſerved his time, being too Maſterly for a Servant, and having a Natural A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion to ſo ſordid a Profeſſion, his higher Thoughts led him to a contemptible Opinion of at leaſt ſo ſlovenly an Occupa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Throat-cutting, poſſibly fancying himſelf Capacitated for more manly Attacks than upon Tame Heifers and blearing Sheep, inſomuch that he got looſe from that Subjection by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of all ſides; and then Marrying a Countrywoman there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>about, he took the <hi>Bear Inn</hi> in <hi>Cheſſon.</hi> In this Poſt his Fortune was no ways anſwerable to his Expectation, our Hero found not half. Trade enough to make the Pot Boyl; till 'twas obſerved that once in four or five Days a Jolly Troop of well Mounted Gallants wou'd viſit his Houſe, and by ſpending and Revelling at a very high rate, make a little amends for the ſlow doings all the Week beſides. 'Twas thought that this Jovial Gang laid the firſt Foundation of his Ambition in Emulating thoſe Gay Examples; and thence aſpiring to the Mercurial Life of a Rover and Son of Fortune. For very ſoon after, our Spigget Merchant made his Abdication from <hi>Cheſſon,</hi> for farther Walks abroad, and bolder Adventures. Now his poor Domeſtick Houſhold-ſtuff, his Wife, as troubleſome Lumber was dropt at a poor cott near <hi>Enf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ild;</hi> where nevertheleſs, though his now more elevated Gentleman Appetite diſdained the Deſpicable courſe Fare of an homely Mattimon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>al Diſh, as dayly Feaſting
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:96167:3"/>and Rioting upon the variety of Gay Miſſes, and <hi>Lond<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n</hi> Dames; however he took that care as now and then to drop a <hi>Guinea</hi> in his Travels to Melancholly Spouſe at home; and in fine, to keep her Houſe over her Head, and Bread in Cupboard. I am the more ſhort in this Part of our Sory, as that ſeveral little Pamphlets, already peep'd abroad, have been more prolix in this part of his Life, and therefore I ſhall not treat my Reader with ſo inſipid a Repetition. Nor ſhall I make it my Buſineſs to Enumerate every particular groſſer Robbery, which affording little Matter more than the rough Compliment of <hi>Stand and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver,</hi> would conſequently make but a dull and undivertiſing Narration, ſuch as the Robbing the <hi>Lancaſhire</hi> Carrier, his Butchery of the poor Horſes at <hi>Mimms Waſh,</hi> or any other of his heavyer Feats of Activity, as the tireſome Pamphleteers upon the ſame Subject have fooliſhly done before me. No, the deſign of this Treatiſe is only to ſelect thoſe more Intriguing and more Comical Rencounters of his, of which kind near four years Reign of his cannot want Variety; and thereby make my Reader a more pleaſant Entertainment.</p>
            <p>To return therefore to our Captain, and ſhorten the Satur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nine part of our Hiſtory. I ſhall only inform you that to qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lify him for this reſolute Imployment, he was one of the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Dear-ſtealers in the Nation, an excerciſe highly in faſhion with him in his very Prentiſhip; and a very good Initiation to him for the Hazards and Hardineſs of the Highway. In the beginning of his performance for ſome conſiderable while he excerciſed his Proweſs in Robbing alone. But when Time had laid Honour and Reputation upon his Back, a great many young Adventurers were proud of Liſting under ſo brisk a Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and the Jolly Troop increaſing he acquired the honourable Title of Capt. <hi>Whitney.</hi> And now notwithſtanding I have ſought and received the moſt ſubſtantial Authority for the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit and Truth of the following Narrations; however, I have not tyed my ſelf up to that nicety, as to be too critical in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act order and ſucceſſion of his Exploits, that difficult and need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Information is more than our Subject requires, or my Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der may expect; as to all other. Points we value our ſelves up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on playing the Faithful Hiſtorian.</p>
            <p>But before I proceed to our Hiſtory, I ſhall only tell you that his firſt Deſertion of his Inn-keeping, was on this occaſion: One of the Gang of his high-flown Gueſts being Apprehended about four years ſince for ſuſpicion of Robbery, his kind Hoſt was pleaſed to offer himſelf and another Man, a pretended <hi>Londoner,</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:96167:3"/>to be his Bayl before Sir <hi>H—G—</hi> a worthy Juſtice of Peace of <hi>Hartfordſhire;</hi> but Seſſions ſoon after Drawing on, the Principal and both the Seconds, all three of the Birds were fairly flown, and from that day the Captain was no farther ſeen or heard of thereabouts, but in the Fame and Trumpets of his publick Atcheivements, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And ſo to come to our Memoirs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Being one Evening alone upon the Parade near <hi>Newbery,</hi> he over took a good Motherly neat Country woman, and a very Pretty young Creature her Daughter, both indifferently Mount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and in very deep Tears and Lamentation. The Captain could not forbear looking with a great deal of Compaſſion up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Sweetneſs and Innocence of the young Damſel, eſpecially in that wayling condition. And hereupon (tho indeed already ſuſpecting the Cauſe) he asked the occaſion of ſo much ſawcy ſorrow, that durſt give ſo violent a Diſturbance to the ſweet Eyes of ſo pretty a Creature. The Mother, of the two, being the readier with an Anſwer, immediately told him, <hi>That her ſelf and her Daughter had been moſt inhumanly Rob'd of the ſum of forty Pounds, that they were both utterly undone, for that very Money was her Daughters Portion, the all in the whole World ſhe had to give her, and that to morrow ſhe was to have been Marryed to a very honeſt Countryman, a Mealman, near</hi> Newbery, <hi>that had long Wooed her; and that now the Loſs of the Money would not only undoubtedly break off the Match, but likewiſe be the utter inevitable Ruine of her poor miſerable Child.</hi> The Captain, who preſently ſmelt the Rat, and was partly ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied which of his Gang had done this Execution; neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs felt a great deal of tenderneſs for the Afflicted Damſel, and endeavour'd to pacify both Mother and Daughter, by telling them, <hi>That the Bridegroom intended, could never be ſuch a Barbarian ſure, as to deſert his contracted Bride for what was her Misfortune, not her Fault. That conſidering the Beauty and Charms of ſo pretty a Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture he was going to poſſeſs certainly ſo poor a Trifle as the inconſiderable Sum of Forty Pounds, would break no ſquares, nor make any Bars to either of their Happineſs. Alas,</hi> replyed the Mother, <hi>you are a Gentleman, and I ſuppoſe a Man of an Eſtate, and forty Pounds may be little in yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Pocket, but truly, 'tis a great ſum in a poor Countryman's Purſe. A Pox of Mony</hi> (replyed the Captain, interrupting her) <hi>does not he Love her? Ay, Sir,</hi> rep'yed the Young Virgin, <hi>He does Love me, and heartily too, otherwiſe I ſhould not be ſuch a fooliſh Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture as to Sacrifice my whole Life to a man that did not Love me. But, alas, Sir, you Courteirs and Gallants have a great deal higher Notions of Love, than poor Country Folks; Love with us muſt have Conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> go along with it. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d as much Beauty and Charms
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:96167:4"/>and other fine things, as you are pleaſed to lay to my Charge, if my Portion be to ſeek, I may go ſeek for a Husband too. A great deale of Diſcourſe paſt more upon the ſame Subject, but to come to Buſineſs, the Captain offered to Inn with them at <hi>Newberry,</hi> and wait the Lovers intended Viſit next Morning, (as he underſtood he was to meet 'em there) and ſee what per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwading Influence he could have over him, or at leaſt what he would propoſe towards making an Accommodation in this buſineſs. They accepted the Gentlemans kind offer, tho with very little hopes of ſucceſs from it, for they were pretty well aſſured that a few kind pacyfying words, for that was the moſt they could expect from a Stranger, would do bur little in ſo important a Negotiation. As they travelled ſoberly towards the Town, the Captain deſired them to make no Noiſe of their Loſs at the Inn, but huſh their Misfortunes for ſome Reaſons he would give them there: As they travelled along the old woman told him how they had been at <hi>London,</hi> to fetch this mony from a Friend, in whoſe hands it had been Lodged there for her Childs ſake, and afterwards gave him a long Relation of her own Family and her Affairs, in which there was nothing worth the Captains remembrance, except a very comical de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of the hard Labour ſhe had with this poor Girl to bring her into the World, and the harder Labour ſhe had to Nurſe her up.</p>
            <p>When they came to the Inn, the matter was diſcuſs'd over again, where 'twas urged, that the Husband deſign'd was a wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thrifty Man, and would no more Marry a Beggar tho with all the Charms of an <hi>Arch Angel,</hi> then he would build Churches. And in ſhort, nothing but Ruine and Deſpair lay before 'em, for truly the Girle did very much love him, and really had cauſe for it, for he had wooed her 2 whole years to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, with all the Paſſion and Faith imaginable, and more to that purpoſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The Captain by this Time, mightily ſmitten with the young Bride, very frankly offered to lay down the 40 <hi>l.</hi> which he had in Gold about him, to make up the Portion, and reconcile the Lovers. They were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oth aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſht at this ſurprizing Goodneſs, and could not really believe him in Earneſt in ſo great a Favour, unleſs he had ſome hard Terms to joyn with it, and therein they were not deceived, for truly the Captain in all the inſinuating ſmooth Language he could dreſs it, told 'em that he would not lend, but pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent her with the Money, for to lend it, as that he might do, and force her Husband to pay it afterwards, would
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:96167:4"/>not only be a very great hardſhip upon him, but poſſibly make a great fraction in their Peace, and raiſe an irreconcileable Fewd betwixt Man and Wife; no, he would accommodate her on much gentler Terms; what Returne he expected, (as really he could not but be ſo much mercinary) was the happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of this one Nights Lodging with the Bride. The Mother and Daughter, as you may well imagine, were highly ſta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tled at ſuch a Propoſal, which the Capt. had no ways to excuſe, but by urging the ſtrange hold that this young Creature, tho in ſo ſhort a Converſation, had got upon his Heart, with a 100 more paſſionate Expreſſions upon ſo tender a theme to the ſame amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous tune. A very great flood of Tears followed from the fair Eyes at ſo harſh a motion: but to draw matters to a point, and omit the Arguments bandyed on both ſides; the loſs of a Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, the loſs of a Fortune, and indeed all the poor Girls ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation in this World, were ſuch potent conſiderations, that in fine, to repair ſo fatal a Breach, as this Gentlemans kind 40 <hi>l.</hi> would re-cement, the Mothers heart beginning to mollyſy firſt, ſhe could not, though with much Regret, but yeild. And truly to ſoften the Daughter, after ſome ſmall reflections upon the Gentlemans hard terms, ſhe uſed a Motherly Authority, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce her Daughter to Complyance; 'tis true, indeed ſhe obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, that 'twas a little ſevere to rob a poor longing Bridearoom of an expected Virginity; yet conſidering that means might be uſed to make him wholy unſenſible of his Loſs, what the Eye ſaw not the Heart rued not; beſides the hardſhip and Calamity that lay upon her muſt oblige her to a Conſent, which would be a great leſſening to her Fault, under her neceſſity that forced it. The Capt. too exerciſed his ſoftning Talent, and amongſt other preſſing Arguments, he told the young Girl 'twas not ſo hani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous a fault as perhaps ſhe fancied it. The time was when by the cuſtom of ſome Tenures in ſome Countries the Lords of the Mannor claimed the firſt Night with the Bride, and that with the very Husbands conſent, but this gentler Night carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with ſilence and ſecreſy, would be a ten times eaſier and more venial Treſpaſs At laſt, the Fort being won, it was concluded, (after a ſplendid Supper at the Capt's Charge, in which, a chea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Glaſs of Wine had perhaps a little help'd forwards,) that their Bed-chambers being choſen next Room to each other, the Mother ſhould leave the door a-jar on purpoſe for the Captain's admiſſion, and then retire her ſelf to his bed chamber, for the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptain's Accommodation with the Daughter. The Plot thus laid, I dare not recount the Sweets the Capt. taſted at the firſt gathering
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:96167:5"/>of ſuch <hi>unblown Roſes;</hi> 'tis enough to tell you, that the Capt. appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that <hi>ſubſtantial Eloquence</hi> to his ſweet Bed-fellow, as ſoften'd infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely more than all the <hi>ver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>al Rhetorick</hi> he had uſed before; inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that not altogether ſo much repining at the Captain's hard Terms (as we call'd 'em before) ſhe had not quite ſo reſenting a thought of her Bridegroom's Hardſhip, nay truly, before morning (ſuch miraculous operation had one ſhort night wrought) that ſhe could not forbear, amongſt other Endearments, to tell her bed-mate, <hi>That truly her Bridegroom</hi> (as much as we told you ſhe loved him before) <hi>was but an ordinary Countryman, and truly ſhe could wiſh he were but half ſo ſweet a Perſon as himſelf; but that was a happineſs too high for a poor Country Girls Ambition,</hi> &amp;c. How raviſhingly the Capt. ſpent his dear Night, may be better gueſt than told. Let it ſuffice, he was ſo pleas'd with his Bedfellow, that he threw in a Five Pound Peice of Gold to the 40 before ſtipulated.</p>
            <p>Early in the morning the Bridegroom, and ſome few friends at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended the <hi>ſuppoſed Virgin Bride,</hi> and amongſt many Country Jokes, ſome of his friends were pleas'd to <hi>droll</hi> upon the hard Nights Labour he muſt expect, little imagining that the Capt. had taken that Toyl off his hands. The Bride was pleas'd to recommend the Capt. to her Husband's Acquaintance, telling him, that ſhe had fortunately met a Gentleman that proved to be a Couſin of hers, one Mrs. ſuch a one, his ſecond Couſin, being a firſt Couſin to a third Couſin of hers, <hi>Mary</hi> ſuch a one, or ſome ſuch kind of <hi>Altiance</hi> between 'em; inſomuch that ſeveral <hi>mutual Compliments paſt upon the Claiming Kin to ſo Honourable a Relation.</hi> To conclude, the Capt's Affairs not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting him to make one at the Wedding, tho much invited, all the fair Bride at parting could do, was to tell him, her husband's houſe was at ſuch a Place, and to make her husband Joyn with her in the ſame requeſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to conjure him, whenever he travell'd that way, to make their houſe his home; and ſo they ſhook hands, and kiſt, not without a <hi>falling Tear,</hi> a <hi>Pearl</hi> beſtow'd upon the Capt. at parting, from the fair Bride, in ſpight of <hi>all her endeavours to conceal it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Adventure not ending here, it happened that about Ten Months after, the Capt. in his Travels that way, made bold to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of the Invitation aforeſaid, and made the New Couple a Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit at their houſe near <hi>Newberry.</hi> Now it fell out that the poor wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man was then in the Straw, having lain in about 3 Weeks. Here was great Joy of all hands for their long look'd for Gentle Couzen, more particularly on the female ſide. The husband (it being nigh Supper-time) preſently kills a couple of the fatteſt Fowls, and makes preparations for an extraordinary Entertainment; but the good Lady not being ſatisfied with thoſe Regales the houſe could
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:96167:5"/>afford, beſought her dear Spouſe to take a Walk to a Neighbouring <hi>Miller</hi>'s, ſomething above half a Mile off, for a brace of Trouts. The good man offered to ſend his Servant; but the good woman (for Reaſons that ſhall be nameleſs) thought her husband the propereſt meſſenger; telling him, that his Man was ſuch a Blockhead he knew not a Fiſh in ſeaſon from one out of it. No, ſhe was reſolv'd none ſhould manage a Diſh for her Couzen's Entertainment but himſelf. When the good man was upon the march for the Fiſh, the good Dame, who had her Nets to lay, was extreamly fond of her Viſitant; nay, ſhe could not forbear telling him, that the thum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping Boy ſhe ſhow'd him in the Cradle, was his own proper fleſh and blood; deſiring him to number back Weeks and Days to that dear Night with him at <hi>Newberry,</hi> and he ſhould find the Account exactly agreeing: beſides, ſhe was pleas'd, amongſt a great many amorous Careſſes, to let him know, ſhe taſted thoſe bliſſes that Night which were never equall'd ſince, intimating, that there was not Manhood enough at home to go to the making of ſo Luſty a Bantling. This Converſation, aſſiſted by the husband's abſence, made way for ſome nearer and dearer familiarity; and tho, tis true, a green woman, yet the Capt. not valuing colours, and the Lady truſting to the ſtrength of her Conſtitution, gave him the Invitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of laying a foundation for a New Scion from the ſame fruitful Stock. Before the husband's Return, being all alone with the Capt. and being now a little hardier Love-Combitant than in her firſt En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement with him, ſhe laid heads together with him for his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany the whole night with her; the deſign being much fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd by the diſmiſſion of her Nurſe the day before to a new Mrs. Now all things convenient, and the Gueſt-Room for Lodging of Strangers being a lower Parlour, and lying beyond her husband's bed-room, through which he muſt paſs, ſhe durſt not adviſe him to come and ſteal that way up to her Chamber, as being too dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous a hazard. Upon mature reſult, it came to this concluſion, that the Captain having a ſmall back-door into the Yard from his Chamber, and the Room next to hers was a kind of Granary, into which her husband craned up all his Sacks of Meal, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> it was agre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed he ſhould, after the whole houſe was in bed, ſteal out to the Crane, and ſhe would draw him up (being a matter not beyond her ſtrength) into the Granary, and ſo take him to bed with her.</p>
            <p>After this Project was laid, the Husband returned with a Brace and an half of good Trouts, which, together with ſome other Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions, made a ſumptuous Banquet. During Supper-time, amongſt other diſcourſe in praiſe of the Trouts, the Captain was pleaſed to ſay, he was a peice of a Fiſherman himſelf, but all the Trouts he
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:96167:6"/>took were with tickling; which the ſmiling Young Dame was plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to ſay, was a very pretty way of fiſh catching. Bed time draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on, and the Capt. being introduc'd to the Parlour, to his intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Lodging, he undreſt himſelf for Bed; but as ſoon as by all ſigns he found all faſt, he ſlipt on his Coat, Breeches and Shooes only, and ſoftly unbolting the back door. went to the Crane, where the kind Lady above ſoon hoyſted him up; and nothing now but a clear Stage, and from him no Favour, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Thus they continued all night, till a glimmering of day began to appear. But as a ſpight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful peice of <hi>Ill Luck,</hi> the poor husband feaſting a little too heartily in the Entertainment of his Couzen, had a neceſſity to go to the back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide for a certain occaſion. From whence returning, he ſpy'd the Parlour open, at which a little ſurpriz'd, he made bold to peep into the Captain's Room, where by the ſmall dawn of day he plainly perceived the bed empty, ſeeing only the Hat, Wig, and ſome other of the Capt's Accoutrements remaining on the Table. In ſome ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den ſtart hereat, led by an unhappy haſte, he went up Sta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rs in ſome Precipitation, to diſcourſe his dear Sp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e upon the Subject of his ſurpriſe. Juſt at this minute it fell out that the Lovers very careful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly were upon drawing off, and the Lady at the Crane juſt letting him down, when the husband bolting in upon her, ſhe gave a great ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iek and let the Crane go, and the Capt. drop; and he being at that time out of the window, and within 5 or 6 foot of the ground, the ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of <hi>the fall</hi> made a noiſe, and occaſion'd the husband to cry, <hi>Whats that?</hi> but ſhe, after her ſhreik, wiſely flinging her Arms round her hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band's neck, (as if the Effect of her Fright) held him in that <hi>cloſe hug</hi> ſo long till the Capt. had time to recover his chamber. The hu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>band mightily wonder'd at finding his wife in ſuch an unwomanly exerciſe as handing of Cranes; but ſhe, ready provided with an anſwer, told him, <hi>that ſuch a motherly woman had told her it was for her health, and that ſhe had practis'd it for above a week together;</hi> which fatisfi'd the credulous husband; and in anſwer to the ſhreik ſhe made, 'twas <hi>occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion'd</hi> ſhe ſaid, <hi>by her ſtart at the ſudden encounter of her husband at that unſeaſonable hour.</hi> All matters thus adjuſted, the hour of up-riſing drew on, and the Capt. complaining of the new Cyder he had drank <hi>over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plentifully laſt night,</hi> cunningly gave his hoſt ſome ſort of hints, <hi>that it had open'd more back-doors than one</hi> and ſo left him to believe, that his miſſing him from his bed proceeded from the very ſame occaſion of his own <hi>over-early</hi> riſing in the Morning; and conſequently huſht <hi>all</hi> farther curioſity; inſomuch that nothing but Mirth attended a very <hi>chearful bre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>kfaſt.</hi> So the Capt. having his <hi>Belly well fill'd,</hi> and poſſibly the good Dame hers ſo too, parting drew on, and ſo making a <hi>ſmall Oblation</hi> of a <hi>Broad Price,</hi> to buy the Boy a <hi>Coral,</hi> he took his <hi>Leave</hi> of his kind Landlord and kinder Landlady.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:96167:6"/>
            <p>Another comical Adventure of his: He over-took a Jacobite Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain bound towards <hi>London,</hi> pretty well mounted <hi>(en Cavalier)</hi> with a good Sword, a brace of Piſtols, and other ſuitable Habile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; the Captain, who never fear'd a ſingle Adverſary though never ſo martially accoutred (and perhaps had never leſs occaſion than here) was pleas'd fairly to bid him <hi>Stand and Deliver:</hi> Stand and Deliver, dear Joy, reply'd the poor Teague (being indeed a true Hero of the Bogland-breed) letting fall his Bridle upon his Horſe-neck, both Eyes and Hands up-lifted, and almoſt Thunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruck with two ſuch terrible hard Words; and what muſt ee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver and pleaſe thy ſweet Face! Your Purſe, you Dog (anſwered the Captain.) My Purſe, noble Shoul; I profeſs indeed ee have a Purſe, and dat Purſe have 20 Guinea's in the Belly of it; but by my Shalvation, dear Joy, if dou do taake it from me (as by St. <hi>Patrick</hi> I hope dou wilt not) me ſelf and three other noble Eeriſh Captains more, muſt be force to make ſtarve for three whole Mont toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; ford is 20 Guinea is de whole Sum dat ee have gather from de noble Friend in de Country, to keep my ſhelf and de other three to buy Bread, and Drink, and Snuſh, for all five of us, from <hi>Whit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſontide</hi> to <hi>Chriſtmas,</hi> dat be three whole long Winter Mont: And dat dou mayſt believe, ſweet Collonel, dat de poor Eeriſh Captain do ſcorn to make Lie upon thee ſweet Faace, look here be de Letter, if dou be Schollar to make read, dat vill tell thee de Trute and the whole Trute, dat dis 20 Guinea be de noble Bounty of honourable Friends and Couſins in de Country, dat have make Charity to keep me own ſelf and three Broder Captains from make ſtarve. And ſo (ſays the Captain) belike you and your Iriſh Brethren have been ſoliciting your kind Patrons and Benefactors, the Country Jaco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bites, and they have choſen you for their Commiſſary general to raiſe Contributions. By St. <hi>Patrick,</hi> dear Joy, dou have de deep Senſe and de great Shole, and dou ſpeak like de Oracle and de Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet: Ara, Joy, ee had de great Grannum dat was Hang for de great Witch, and by Creeſe ſhe had not half de great Brain-piece as dou have: Verily, as thou ſay, I have been de Commiſhary ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, and have raiſe dis poor 20 Guinea—Damn your wild Iriſh Gibberiſh, reply'd the Captain, and deliver your 20 Guinea's with a Pox to you, and go and beg more like a Scoundrel, or rob like a Gentlemen as I do; what a Plague are you and your Brother Bog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trotters to me? In ſhort, the poor O hone was forced to diſmantle the whole three Months Fortification and Proviſion; but with ſo doleful and rueful a Countenance, that the Captain cou'd not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:96167:7"/>ſmiling at the extraordinarineſs of the Figure; and being a little diverted with the odd Phys of the Fellow, and the lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Moan he made for his Loſs, he rode along with him, and exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined him how he came to be a Captain? By my Showl, dear Joy, (quoth Teague) ee will tell dee de whole Story of all mee Renown and Glory, if dou vill promiſe to make Mercy and Compaſſion up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me. Well, well (ſays the Captain) tell me the Story firſt, and truſt to my mercy afterwards, as I find you deſerve it. Hereupon the poor Teague, very formally tells him, That in the beginning of his dear Maſter King <hi>James</hi> his Reign, he came over with a great many hundred more of his dear Countrymen, in thoſe bleſſed days of Iriſh Honour and Preferment; that truly having a great mind to ſpeak a word to his Majeſty for a Captains Plaace, a wicked Heretick Engliſh Man, had the Impudence to ask him Half a Crown to write a Petition for him; but truly, Mony being hard with him, he did buy a white Sheet of gilt Paaper for a Half-penny, and he did preſent it to his Majeſty's Graaſh at St. <hi>James</hi> his Park, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his Knee; and did tell his Majeſty <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ere was de Paper for de Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition for de Captain's Place in de Iriſh Army: And that his Engliſh Majeſty's Grace being very kind and generous, and knowing his want and occaſion as well as himſelf, did order a Letter to his Iriſh Majeſty's Grace <hi>Tyrconnel</hi> (for he, God bleſs him, had Half a Crown to pay for Writing though poor Teague had not) and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon he did kiſs his Royal Hand, and return to his own Country; and his Graace <hi>Tyrconnel</hi> did give him a Commiſſion, and dub him a Captain. Here, in ſine, he run on at a high Rate, how many Heroick Feats he had perform'd, how many Men, Captains and Collonels, he had kill'd with his own Hand, and what extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Proofs of Manhood he had ſhewn in all the Battles from before <hi>Londonderry</hi> to <hi>Agrim.</hi> Our Captain, whoſe Patience almoſt tired, having heard him out with a ſeeming Admiration of ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nown'd a Commander, could not forbear throwing in this unlucky Queſtion; Prithee, dear Captain, ſays be, if thou haſt been in ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Skirmiſhes, and Battles, and Sieges, and behav'd thy ſelf in all of 'em with ſuch ſignal Teſtimonials of thy undaunted Valour; how comes it about, that with a good Horſe under thee, a pair of Piſtols before thee, and all things anſwerable, thou haſt ſo tamely and coldly ſuffered one ſingle Man, no better provided than thy ſelf, to rob thee of all thou haſt in the World, to keep thee from ſtarving, without the leaſt diſpute or reſiſtance for ſo important a Preſervation? Alas, dear Joy, replies Teague, dou doſt not know de great occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:96167:7"/>dat tie up my Arm; for I have made ſolemn Vow and Oat up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on de Virgin Pſalter, dat I will ne're draw Sword nor handle Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon, till that bleſt day when my great Maſter ſet Foot agen upon Engliſh Ground. Oh, is it ſo! Says the Captain, then you have ſworn you'll ne're fight till King <hi>James</hi>'s Return; and therefore, in complaiſance to that religious loyal Oath, you ſtood ſtill to be rob'd. By St. <hi>Patrick,</hi> and de Devil taake me, ſo I did (crys Teague.) Oh dear Joy, dou doſt not know de Honour and Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of an Oat; ee wou'd not break my Oat for ten thouſand Worlds: No, I perceive ſo (replies the Captain.) To con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, the Captain being highly and humbly preſs'd, by his Jaco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bite Petitioner, for a little pity and mercy upon his great Poverty, at laſt he was ſo molifyed, that he reſolved he would not ſtarve four Men by one Robbery, and ſo e'ne return'd him his Purſe and Guinea's again. Poor Teague was ſo highly tranſported at this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expected Favour, that he gave him a hundred Prayers; but above all, beſought him to take care of his ſweet Life, and not fall into the Heretick Hands of Law, till his great Maſter came to his Crown again; which would be as ſoon as ever King <hi>Lewis</hi> could land him on Shore, and lead him to <hi>Whitehall;</hi> and then if he had commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ten thouſand Robberies, this one favour to poor Teague, ſhould ſeal him a Pardon for 'em all.</p>
            <p>Our Captain, more eſpecially in the beginning of his Travels, was extream hardy, and would daily venture into ſeveral Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies in all Parts of the Town, but chiefly in the Out-parts, as <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhopſgate-street, Minories, Spittle-fields,</hi> &amp;c. and was many times his own Intelligencer where to ſet a good Prize, through his diſcovery which way Mony travell'd, and where a lumping Booty was to be gotten. He happen'd one Evening to drink a Glaſs of Wine with an old Fellow, formerly an Alderman of the City of <hi>Durham,</hi> and pretty ſtrong in Pocket; the Captain being that time in a modeſt black Suit, profeſt himſelf a piece of a Doctor of Phiſick, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the Alderman, in the mirth of his brisk Cups, began to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boſome ſome little part of his Soul, and tell him, He had made an Aſſignation with a very pretty young Girl, and the Morrow-night was to Bed with her all night; but, truly, being within a Year or two of Threeſcore, and under the Roſe, a pretty Weather-beaten Fornicator, really he was afraid he ſhould not hold out, to perform anſwerable to his deſire in the Enjoyment of ſo ſweet a Creature; and, therefore, if 'twere poſſible for him to get any ſtrengthning Cordial to invigorate Nature, and make him a little brisk for that
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:96167:8"/>one dear night, he would grutch no Reward to the Ingenious Artiſt that would accommodate him with ſuch a favour. The Captain immediately engaged to ſerve him in it, and that he would prepare him a Bolus, and ſend it him to Morrow-morning, that ſhould make him an abſolute Boy of 22, ſo vigorous a Lover, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and indeed make him perform Wonders; that he had had experience of the Preparation already, and had gotten good Gold by it. This gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Promiſe extreamly inliven'd the old Spark, who paying the whole Shot, about one in the morning they ſhook Hands, and part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, with a Promiſe of a Gratuity, according to the Skill of his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor, and the Merit of his Medicine. Accordingly, the Captain makes uſe of a Quack, a Friend of his, and ſends him in the morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Pot of Electuary, with Directions to take the quantity of a large Walnut, about 3 in the Afternoon, and about Bed-time he ſhould find the Effects deſired to his Hearts content. The night after the Doctor and Patient, about the hour of 9, had agreed to meet at the ſame Tavern, and there the Alderman was to make him a Largeſs of acknowledgment, proportionable to the Raptures he taſted in the ſoft Arms of his ſweet Bed-fellow, and the proweſs and puiſſance he had received from his inſpiring Electuary. They both met at the hour preciſely, and our new Doctor ſaluting his Patient, and inquiring how Matters ſtood with him? Stood! with a Pox, replies the Alderman. Ay Friend, how and how didſt thou perform? How many dear Bouts old Boy? Was it not rare Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick? Did I not tell you what Miracles it would work? Hold a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle (quoth Alderman) fair and ſoftly: I tell you and your Doctor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, never was Man ſo abuſed as I have been; Electuary in the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil's Name! If this be your Cordial, with a vengeance? Why how no Man, replies the Doctor, ſure you do but banter with me; I'll ſtand by my Electuary to the laſt Penny of my Eſtate, and anſwer the Compoſition to the whole Colledge of Phyſicians; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore prithee ſpeak plain, out with it Man; what Effects, what Operation, old Lad? Operation! (quoth Alderman) with a pite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous mortifyed Look. Ay Friend, reply'd the Captain, Operation. 'Tis impoſſible that ſuch a Preparation ſhould fail; and therefore to make no Secret with thy Bodily Confeſſor, but in the Name of ſoft Love and ſweet Lechery, how and how my Heart of Oak? In ſhort, after much preſſing from his importunate Quack, to know the full force and effects, what it had done, and how it had wrought, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> at laſt, after a very deep Sigh, this doleful Anſwer broke out. Only three Stools (quoth Alderman) that's all. Stools, replied
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:96167:8"/>the Captain, hardly holding his Countenance at ſo comical an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer. Lord, Sir, 'tis impoſſible. Ay, Stools, quoth the Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, nothing in the whole World, but three wicked filthy Stools; a Plague of your beaſtly Phyſick. The Captain ſeem'd very much concerned (hardly crediting the Relation) at ſuch an unexpected Operation; and therefore deſired the Alderman to tell him, how and when, and how much he took of it. So that the Alderman made anſwer, that truly he took it about the Hour of Three, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to preſcription; and that being reſolved not to fail in the Doſe, but lay a more than ordinary Foundation for his intended Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licity, as he had order'd the quantity of one Walnut, to make ſure work, he had taken the quantity of two. Ounds, Man, replied the Captain, you ſpoil'd all; two Doſes at once! Death, I won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it had not kill'd you; three Stools! Nay, 'tis well you come off ſo well. Wou'd any, but a Madman, outrun his <hi>Recipe!</hi> and be wiſer than his Doctor! and ſo make Poiſon of his Phyſick. In fine, the Captain carried on the Rebuke with a very high Hand, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>primanded his Patient's Folly and Frenzy at no ſmall rate, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that the Alderman cried Peccavi, imputed his Misfortune to his own Indiſcretion, and the Doctor recover'd his Reputation as fair and whole again as his Heart cou'd wiſh. And now the poor lamenting Alderman unboſoming his whole Load of Sorrow, told him, how the contrary Effects of his Bolus had utterly diſabled him from taſting any Delights at all with his young Bedfellow; nay, what was worſt of all, it being his miſchance to be lock'd up in the Room, together with her, and the Key in another Body's hand, not able to get out, he was forced to make uſe of the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber-pot, and that, as the Devil would have it, not large enough for the treble Diſcharge aforeſaid, he was compell'd to make uſe of the Chimney for diſpoſing the Overplus, to his great ſhame and confuſion, being not only a moſt impotent, but likewiſe a moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſavoury Bedfellow. And all he could do to excuſe his Calamity, was by telling the whole naked Truth to the poor defeated Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and laying the whole Fault upon the Villany of the Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian. That the Girl was kindly pleas'd (much more than he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved) to commiſerate rather than laugh at him, and that truly having atoned for his Miſcarriage by a brace of Jacobuſſes next Morning, he had made a new Contract with her, and ſent her down to a Lodging at <hi>North-hall,</hi> whether himſelf was next Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to follow her, and there to enjoy her for the whole Water<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſon.
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:96167:9"/>The Captain offer'd his Service of waiting him thither, having (as he told him) a long Inclination to a little Diverſion at thoſe Wells, which the Alderman kindly embraced; whether lovingly letting out together early next Morning, the Doctor, at a convenient opportunity in the Road, was pleas'd to give his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient a gentle Purgation of about fifty odd Pounds, and ſome other ſmall Toys about him, as a Ring, Watch, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and ſo left the poor Limberham as feeble in Purſe as before in Back, to his beſt Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment of his <hi>North hull Bona Roba.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Another no leſs divertive Narrative we have to make you, <hi>viz.</hi> That one Evening, according to his cuſtomary hardineſs of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany-keeping, he fell into the Society of three or four ſturdy Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cobites of good Quality and Faſhion. One of which a Gentleman of a conſiderable Eſtate, and a little above mid-way, between 20 and 30 Years old, lay under an obligation of never cutting his Beard, till K. <hi>James</hi> return'd; and having commenced his Oath as far ſince as the firſt day of Abdication, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and being naturally a handſom black Man, his overgrown, Raven-colour'd Excreſcence in ſo many Years, unhappily brindled with a mixture of white, had reacht down almoſt to his Waſte, and perhaps altogether was not ſo modiſh nor ſo beauiſh a Figure, as otherwiſe ſo accompliſht a Gentleman might have made. Nevertheleſs his high Adoration for his old Maſter, and his Veneration for the Solemneſs of his Vow ſuperſeded all other Conſiderations, and no Advice nor Intereſt whatever could prevail with our reſolute <hi>Nazareen</hi> to part with the leaſt Twig from ſo ſpreading a Buſh. Nay, as ill luck wou'd have it, the Gentleman was at that time fal'n deſperately in Love with a young and moſt beautiful Lady, who had no diſlike to his Perſon, nor any diſreliſh to his Addreſſes, only ſhe utterly refuſed to marry him, till he would yield to ſacrifice that unweildy Crab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, and bring a ſmooth Chin to her ſoft Embraces. In fine, his Beard being the only Bar to his Felicity, the Conſummation, he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, was wholly obſtructed on no other account. This Subject being a great part of the preſent Converſation, ſome of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany were pleas'd to applaud his Maſculine Reſolution, in keeping firm to his Loyal Vow, whatever the Effeminate Whiſpers of Love might perſwade to the contrary. Others were a little more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clining to the Lady's Party, and cou'd not but approve her Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in not expoſing her ſoft Lips and ſmooth Cheeks to ſuch rude and barbarous Briſtles. The Gentleman for his part avow'd, that
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:96167:9"/>he could half hang or drown to poſſeſs ſo ſweet a Creature, never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs could no ways recede from his Oath; and if ſhe perſiſted wholly inexorable, whatever his Sufferings would prove, he muſt continue deaf, even to the leaſt thought of violation of ſo ſolemn an Engagement. In fine, as faſt and as deep as the Lady was in his Heart, his Beard was as faſt rooted too; and nothing but the Return of his great Maſter, with the bright Sword in his Hand, ſhould ever bring the gentle Razour to his Chin.</p>
            <p>Many Arguments were bandied round amongſt this jolly Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, and a great Conteſt of Love and Honour, betwixt Beard and Miſtreſs, was no ſmall piece of the Entertainment, and amongſt the many Bumpers to the old Maſter, and the young Lady, a good Health to the honourable Beard, made one or two cheerful Glaſſes go round extraordinary. The Captain being as high a Jacobite as the beſt of them, took occaſion highly to commiſerate the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man's unhappineſs in the ſtrange obſtinacy of his fair Adored; for that was the beſt Name he could give to her unreaſonable Denials, of ſo accompliſht a Gentleman, on ſo trivial an Account. What the Devil muſt the Women in ſome parts of the World do for Husbands, if the Objection of a Beard were a ſufficient refuſal? Nay, what muſt all our great Grand-mothers here in <hi>England</hi> have done in the old Days of Gravity, when thicker Chins and thinner Foretops were in faſhion? Some Beard, not all Perriwig; a little lower Tire, not all upper Tire, Curl and Friz. For his part, he did not doubt but if he had the Honour of ſeeing this fair Lady, but he ſhould be ſo powerful an Orator in his behalf, as to reduce her to reaſon, and make an intire Accommodation in the Affair: Nay, ſomething (he proceeded) whiſper'd him, that he was cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly born to do the Gentleman ſome ſervice in this Buſineſs, and undoubtedly obtain him his Lady. The Gentleman could not but return him his hearty thanks for the Zeal he expreſt in his behalf, and that truly ſince all Interceſſion and Eloquence had hitherto pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved unſucceſsful, nevertheleſs, if he pleas'd to try his abler Rheto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick in the matter, he ſhould be proud of his good Company at the Lady's at Dinner to Morrow, ſhe living not above a dozen Miles out of Town, and whither an Hour and a half's riding in the cool of the Morning would bring 'em ſo early Viſitants as to nick the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy's upriſing. Hands being ſhook upon it, and the next Morning's loving Journey accordingly concluded, the Company ſoon after broke up, and the Captain fail'd not to awake the Gentleman out
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:96167:10"/>of his Bed next Morning, and to call our amorous Knight Errant for Mount and Away. The Gentleman, on his ſide, took no Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant with him, only the Captain had his Friend, a Gentleman who had occaſion of travelling that way, and would make one to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe the good Company. So all three merrily jogging on, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venience ſoon offer'd, when the Captain deſiring to ſearch the Depth of the Gentleman's Pocket, the Gentleman, though other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe pretty brisk, yet well remembring, that two to one, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> was an old Proverb, was forced peaceably to unhorſe, and ſurrender at diſcretion, and diſcumber his Pocket of a Gold-Watch, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout half a hundred Yellow-Boys, being at that time his whole Cargo. Nay, ſays the Captain, ſince you have ſo very generouſly reſign'd, though, perhaps, I may have ſurpriz'd you in this unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected Treatment, nevertheleſs I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>all be as big as my Promiſe in ſerving you with your Miſtreſs, a Compenſation that ſhall over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pay theſe inconſiderable Trifles: And therefore, <hi>Tom,</hi> (ſays he) turning to his Comrade, Where are the Snippers? Here, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, replies his Mate, pulling out of his Pocket a large Pair of Barber's Sciſſors. To come to the point, They over-maſter'd the poor Gentleman, and getting both upon him, they held him down by main force, till <hi>Tom</hi> made a hard ſhift to ſnip off intirely juſt one ſide of his Beard, cloſe to his Face; then giving him fair leave to riſe, the Captain addreſt himſelf in this manner: Look you, Sir, ſays he, here's Love and Honour reconcil'd. You have ſworn, you would never conſent to cut your Beard, till K. <hi>J.</hi> returned; and now thank Heav'n for raiſing you thoſe Friends that have cut it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out your conſent. You have ſworn you'll wear a Beard, Right; but you have not ſworn you'll wear one ſide of one, when t'other's off. Your Miſtreſs has ſworn, ſhe will not marry you with your Beard on; and I'll be ſworn you have but half a Beard on to trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble her, and when you have ſworn the next kind Barber you meet to take the other half off, you may be fairly ſworn yourſelf to live and die her ever faithful Servant; and both your old Maſter and young Miſtreſs have a true and loyal Vaſſal of you, with neither Oath broken on one ſide, nor Love loſt of the other: And ſo pray preſent my humble Service to your fair Bride, for now I may ſafely call her ſo, and reſt contented that your two humble Servants here are the beſt Cutbeards you ever met with, and have as honeſtly earn'd and deſerv'd your Watch and the few paltry Guinea's you have paid us, as a Thief deſerves a Halter.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:96167:10"/>
            <p>The Gentleman how unkindly ſoever he might reſent this Inſult and Raillery upon him, however partly as overpowered, but chiefly ſatisfied in the plain Truth of the caſe, (how drollingly ſoever the Captain had worded it,) cou'd not forbear, after two or three hearty Oaths, telling the Captain, that By G—he was an honeſt fellow and had done his work for him; And therefore ſince he had found out ſo dexterous a Diſpenſation to his long troubleſome vow, and open'd ſo fair a path to his Mrs's Arms upon the Honour of a Gentleman he truly forgave him all he had took from him; To which were it twice as much he was hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily welcome; And to ſhew him he was ſo, he kindly invited him to his Wedding, binding it with an hundred Oaths that not a Hair of his Head ſhould ſuffer, if he would grant him that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of his Company; The Captain ſeeing him ſo heartily preſs it, gave him as ſolemn a promiſe that he would make one at the Nuptials, and accordingly agreed that he ſhould give him notice of the day by a Penny Poſt Letter left in ſuch a name at ſuch a Houſe in <hi>London.</hi> 'Twas not ten days after, before the inviting Letter came, and the Day appointed, the Nuptials to be cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brated at his own Seat about 30 Miles from <hi>London.</hi> In the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternoon about two hours after the Bridal Feaſt, a jolly Troop of about half a ſcore of Sparks well mounted, all with half Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zords Lighted at the Gentlemans Gate, and deſired admiſſion as Maſquers to entertain the Bride and Bridegroom, which was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately granted, and they all very ceremoniouſly introduced. The Captain took the Bridegroom aſide and diſcovered his Face, telling him he had kept his word, but withal deſiring his ſecre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, at the ſame time aſſuring him, that tho' the reſt of his Gang were all Brothers of his own Myſtery, yet as this Viſit was pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Honour and Friendſhip, neither himſelf nor any one of his Honourable Gueſts, ſhould ſuffer the leaſt farthing either going or coming, by himſelf or any one of his ſmall Troop. The Gentleman no ways diſtruſting his Fidelity, the beſt half of the Night was paſt in Dancing, Feaſting and Revelling, the Maſque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raders performing in all points to Admiration, and gaining as far upon all the uningaged Female Hearts in the Company, as nimble Heels and half Faces could puſh towards a Conqueſt. When the Bride, not till near Cock-crowing, could get looſe, ſtoln out by her kind Bridemaids, to the envied felicity of a Nuptial Bed, and the brisk now ſmooth-chind Lover was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring to follow her, the Captain took his leave being extream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly careſt by his Honourable Hoſt.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:96167:11"/>
            <p>About three months after the Captain had ſet a Booty of two hundred pound, being ſome part of the Pelf of an Overgrown Miſer travelling up with it to <hi>London</hi> in the <hi>Banbury</hi> Stage Coach. It happen'd that the Coach was full, having five Women be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides Sir <hi>Mammon</hi> himſelf in it, who infinitely diſobliged his Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male Fellow Travellers by ſmoaking all the way a ſort of a <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mudas</hi> Funk, ſtrong and cheap, and though highly courted to ſome moderation in his Mundungo, yet being an ill natured old chuff, and paſt the Age of Complaiſance, not all the intreaties of the Fair Sex could prevail, inſomuch that he had almoſt poyſon'd or at leaſt half choak'd them. But the Captain deſtined for their Deliverance with 3 or 4 more of his Retinue, riding up to the Coach deſired the favour of eaſing the Coach-box of two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred pound burthen. The old Muckworm as (you may ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine) in no ſmall conſternation at this mortal Alarm, ſo fright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that 'twas hard to diſtinguiſh which end of him ſtunk worſt; the Ladies were a little ſtartled at firſt, but the Captain ſoon diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſipated their fears by profeſſing all the kindneſs and civility they could deſire, being indeed always generous to that Sex. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever after he had uncaſed our fat old Fox he ſpyed a Diamond Ring upon one of the Ladies Fingers, and a Necklace of Pearl upon anothers Neck, both which he was pleas'd to requeſt, which were accordingly granted him; only the young Miſs from whom he took the Necklace being not above thirteen years old fell in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a deſperate fit of crying for the Loſs of her Necklace, which the Captain perceiving, in kind pity returned it her again; and not to be partial in his favours was going to do the like by the Lady from whom he took the Ring, making her a very cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Complement beſeeching the whole fair Companies Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, avowing that ſoft Sex ſhould have no reaſon to complain of Captain <hi>Whitney,</hi> whatever murmurs the old Hunk, the gruff Sir with them might conceive againſt him.</p>
            <p>The Lady at the name of <hi>Whitney</hi> utterly refuſed the return of her Ring, deſiring him to wear it for her ſake, telling him that he had helpt her to the beſt Husband in Chriſtendom, and ſo ſmall a preſent was the leaſt Acknowledgment of ſo ſignal an Obligation, deſiring him withal to accept of a Glaſs of <hi>Aqua Mirabilis,</hi> ſo drinking to him out of a Glaſs Bottle his own Health, not forgetting his Man <hi>Tom,</hi> the beſt mad Shaver in the three Kingdoms; the Captain pledged her, and dealt the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies Health round amongſt his Brothers of the <hi>Pad,</hi> and ſo took his leave, having at leaſt ſo far obliged them all, that the Old
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:96167:11"/>Tobacco-monger had broken his Pipe for madneſs at the loſs of his Money, and this laſt ſad Whiff had put him ſo out of all his patience, or thoughts of Smoking, that the Air began a little to clear again amongſt 'em; But of all his Adventures this follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is perhaps the boldeſt and braveſt. Amongſt his Intelligencers he had been advertiſed of ſeven hundred Guineas that a perſon of very high Quality, and a great Cock-fighter, had taken up, and ſuch a day was to move home with them about thirty Miles Weſtward, and accordingly a ſubſtantial Attaque was reſolved upon at ſuch a Poſt in the Road; but as matters fell out, a Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got and a Glaſs extraordinary in the Gentlemans Head mounted him a day ſooner than reſolved, inſomuch that the Captain was defeated of the Prize, his whole Gang being over-reacht by coming a day after the Fair, and the Gentleman reaching Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour with the <hi>Cargo</hi> ſafe within Walls and Sanctuary. This Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appointment vext the Captain to the Soul, but reſolved not to give over the Game as deſperate as it ſeem'd, he at laſt invent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed one of the moſt politick and hardieſt Stratagems that poſſibly was ever undertaken; which take as follows.</p>
            <p>The Gentleman one day ſoon after, as cuſtomary with him, taking his Horſe, (without any Ceremony of Retinue or Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants) to Dine with another Countrey-Gentleman about half a dozen Miles off, in the Evening returning on the Road, and within two Miles of home, he was aſſaulted by five High-way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, who led him about ſix or ſeven Pole aſide into a By-Lane, but not out of ſight of the Road; there they diſmounted him, took away his Watch, and that little Money he had about him, and not contented with that, ſtrip'd him of his Coat, Hat, and embroider'd Waſtcoat, binding him hand and foot, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving to drag him up higher in the By-Lane out of hearing, and ſight of the Road, there to gag him, and leave him bound in a Ditch all night. This Barbarity, you may well imagine, was a very terrible Apprehenſion to the unhappy Gentleman, who though not valuing his inconſiderable Loſs, nevertheleſs the Dread of being expoſed almoſt naked all night, ſuggeſted little leſs than his certain Death from ſo much Inhumanity. But juſt in this doleful Minute of Horrour and Deſpair, it happened that a Gentleman very well dreſt, and nobly well mounted, attended by a Servant in the <hi>Norſolk</hi> Livery, and as well mounted as his Maſter, travelling that way, who diſcovering a pack of Thieves with an unfortunate Prey in their Talons, <hi>Lamn me</hi> ſays he <hi>what's yonder? Thieves!</hi> At this his Man and he both putting
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:96167:12"/>Spurs to their Horſes, gallopped in amongſt them, when the Maſter diſcharging a Piſtol at the head of the firſt he met, who immediately dropt, and the Man as liberal of his Fire as his Maſter, a very brisk Encounter enſued, and Lightning and Thunder ſoon followed on both ſides; and when all their Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tillery was ſpent, they came to dint of Sword, to hew and ſlaſh: But to bring our Battle to a Concluſion Victory at length de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared for the generous Deliverer, the Thieves either vanquiſht or cowd began to give ground and move off in ſome precipita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; four of 'em, (two of which were he that firſt fell, and another who the Noble Stranger had cruppered and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounted, who were neither ſo mortified, but they made a ſhift to recover their Saddles,) rod off full ſpeed, the fifth only being left priſoner behind; who moſt piteouſly beſeeching mercy from his Conquerour, our Hero was contented to give him a cut croſs the pate, and bid him <hi>Loop Skellum;</hi> he having firſt refunded a Watch and ſome ſmall matter of Money, and what elſe they had before taken from the Gentleman. Here our generous Champion and his Man both diſmounted to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bind the poor Gentleman, who could ſcarce forbear acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging his Gratitude for ſo ſignal a Deliverance upon his knees. But amongſt other Careſſes humbly deſiring to know to whom he owed this extraordinary protection; The Stranger was plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to anſwer him his Name was <hi>B. H.</hi> Here the Gentleman renewed his Acknowledgments to his Deliverer, telling him he was no Stranger to that Right Honourable Name, though it was his firſt happineſs of being acquainted with his Perſon, more eſpecially on ſuch an occaſion, under ſuch a Load of Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations received from him. Amongſt other expreſſions of his Gratitude, he humbly beſought the felicity of doing his Houſe the honour of Entertaining him that night, which Invitation our kind <hi>B. H.</hi> embraced, declaring indeed that it was ſome part of his way, being deſigned ſome few days hence for a great Horſe Race near <hi>Salisbury.</hi> I will not particularize the Gallant Treatment our Right Honourable Gueſt received that night; let it ſuffice that no Intreaties could beg any longer ſtay than morning, though infinitely ſollicited, reſolving to take the Cool before Sun-riſe for his departure toward <hi>Sarum.</hi> The Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man being early up to entertain him, and viſiting him in his Bed-Chamber, our Gallant Gueſt took an occaſion of praiſing the Gentlemans Houſe, the ſtatelineſs of the Seat, Building, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> His kind Landlord proud of any occaſion to entertain him, imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:96167:12"/>intreated him to take a walk into ſome of his beſt Apart ments, and view the Houſe; which motion being readily em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced, he was conducted from Room to Room (the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man being his only Guide and Interpreter in any piece of Paint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Rarity and Antiquity relating to the Houſe or Family) till at laſt he ſhew'd him his own Bed-Chamber. Here our Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable <hi>Norfolk</hi> amongſt other furniture of the Room diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a very large Rich Scrutore, was pleaſed ſmilingly to ſay, Well Sir, and I ſuppoſe that Cabinet there is your Treaſury. Yes Sir, replied the Gentleman, that little Treaſure I have, which lies in a ſmall Room amongſt hard Times and poor Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants. Then Sir, replied our <hi>Norfolk</hi> Spark, a little changing the Air of his face, There's ſeven hundred Guineas there which I have a very preſſing occaſion for. And look you Sir to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riddle your Amazement, for I perceive you are ſurpriz'd, in plain Engliſh you were a ſaver laſt night to be a loſer to day; for inſtead of the Right Honourable <hi>B. H.</hi> I am only the Right Honeſt Captain <hi>Whitney,</hi> and ſo without more Ceremony I muſt have that ſeven hundred pound, or your Life Sir. The Gentleman finding himſelf in no capacity to reſiſt, being at this time naked and unarm'd, and upon unequal Terms; neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs had there been equality in the caſe, yet conſidering he was not ſtockt with more Courage than his Poſt required, being on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a Captain of the Countrey <hi>Militia,</hi> 'tis thought the Conteſt would not have been extraordinary; ſo very patiently unlock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one of his Drawers, he peaceably ſurrendred the ſeven hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Guineas. Nay, continued the Captain, I have ſome few Terms more to annex, which are, That you muſt wait upon me the Stable, and not ſtir out of my ſight; careſs me all the way without a wrinkle in your face, or ſo much as a ſide-glance to any of your Servants that ſhall but hint a diſguſt, and pay me all the Reſpect due to the Right Honourable <hi>B. H.</hi> till my Man and I are both mounted, or you are a dead Man. The Gentleman ſeeing the Piſtol ready ſtuck under the Cloak at his Girdle, and all the ſymptoms of Military Execution upon the leaſt Breach of Articles, moſt religiouſly obſerved the whole Cap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tulation, and with all the Addreſs and Veneration, and a hundred Thanks for all Favours and Honour received, conduct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him to his Horſe, and ſaw him ſafely mounted, when bidding farewell, and giving a little tickle with the Spur, he and his Man trooped off with that Expedition as defied the beſt four Legs in his Stable to overtake them.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:96167:13"/>
            <p>Now Reader, having given you this choice Collection of his livelieſt and ſprightlieſt Adventures, I ſhall only conclude with that laſt Rencounter, the misfortune of which brought him to his Cataſtrophe.</p>
            <p>About <hi>Michaelmas</hi> laſt on the <hi>Eſſex</hi> Road, being that time by chance alone, he met a Gentleman Mounted upon a pretty indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent good Hack, with a Pair of Piſtols before him and his Lady ſingle Horſed, attended by a ſturdy Lout, with a Sword tyed to his Breech. This odds of two to one diſheartned not our brisk Captain, who very fairly perking up to the Maſter, gives him the cuſtomary ſalute of <hi>Stand and Deliver;</hi> The Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, whether thro' ſurprize, or any other conſideration, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Reſiſtance, very patiently delivers him the All he had, being not above five or ſix pounds. The Gentlewoman ſeeing her Husband ſo Cow-hearted, in ſo tame a ſubmiſſion, fell very loud upon him, call'd him a hundred Chicken-ſoul'd Cowards, and in ſhort no name bad enough. The Captian ſeeing the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſo Spirited a <hi>Virago,</hi> addreſt himſelf to her, telling her, the little Money he had taken, was not worth all this Paſſion The Money! Damn the Money, replied the Dame, for though as little as 'tis, 'tis ſomething in an Abdicated Officers Pocket, yet 'tis not that Trifle I am concern'd for, no 'tis the Nature of the Brute, the ſhame of the Coward and Craven that Delivered it, that diſturbs me; A fellow that has had the honour of a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion in his Pocket, and to have a Heart no bigger. Princes are finely help'd up with ſuch doughty Commanders. Himſelf and his overgrown Booby at his Arſe, both of 'em ſuch a pair of Tame Turtles, to ſuffer themſelves to be ſo baſely and ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalouſly rob'd. Death! If I had been half ſo well armed my ſelf, I'd have changed one brace of Bullets with you before I'd have yielded. The Captain was ſtrangely amazed and as highly delighted with the Spirit and Bravery of the Woman, together with no little charm in her Face, to add to his Delight, being indeed a very lovely Creature; And gave her a great many very careſſing Compliments, which the Lady as courteouſly returned, at which the Captain ſeeing the Gray Mare the better Horſe, very generouſly made her a preſent of what he had taken from her Husband, which the Lady thankfully received, telling him, that ſhe had that veneration for ſo much Honour and Bravery, that if ever it were her good fortune to meet him in <hi>London,</hi> ſhe would expreſs her gratitude for his generoſity and her eſteem for his Gallantry in a more ſubſtantial acknowledgment. The
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:96167:13"/>Captain ſwore a great Oath he would make it his buſineſs to find her out there. That you may ſoon do, replied the Lady, if you have old-faſhion'd Religion enough to carry you to the Spaniſh Ambaſſadors Chappel, whither the little Devotion I have brings me generally every Morning. The Captain told her that whatever his own Religion was, his Reſpects to ſo fair a Lady cou'd convert him to any Church, and he ſhould not fail the Pious Aſſignation aforeſaid. But to prevent his Queſt of his fair Inviter at Chappels and High Altars, it was his Fortune to meet her in leſs Holy Ground; For one Morning about five or ſix days after, the Captain muffled in his Cloak and in a Coach with the Windows drawn up, had occaſion to make a ſtand in the <hi>Strand</hi> for one of his Comrades to meet him there. During his ſtop there, through a broken Pane in the Coach Window, he diſcovered the very Lady at a Milliners Shop buying a pair of Gloves and ſome other ſmall matters, which when ſhe had pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed, turning her Face to the Street-ward, a Coach was call'd for her, which the Captain perceiving threw open the door of his Coach, and told the Lady here was one at her Service; The Lady immediately remembring the Face. Oh dear Couzen, ſays ſhe, are you there! And ſo accepting his Kindneſs, imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately ſtept into the Coach to him; Where the Door and Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow where both preſently cloſed again. The Captain very joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully embracing her, and asking whither they ſhould drive; an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer was made, e'ne where he pleas'd. Hereupon the Coach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man was bid to drive to <hi>Knights-bridge,</hi> where lighting at the Swan, a very ſumptuous Dinner was beſpoken, and the Lovers (for ſo I'll venture to call 'em) left to all the Enjoyment and Felicity the Accommodation of ſo Hoſpitable a Houſe could yield 'em. I ſhall not be tedious in telling you, that this Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ended in Love, and the beſt and heartieſt effects of it the Captain could give her. Let it ſuffice the ſatisfaction was infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely pleaſing on both ſides, the Lady amongſt a hundred other Careſſes, aſſuring him, that this was the firſt time ſhe ever wrong'd her Husband in this kind, (at leaſt you have the Ladys word for't if Cuckolding a Coward may be properly called wronging him, being indeed the leaſt he deſerv'd. Amongſt the reſt of the Converſation ſhe told the Captain how her Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band was once a Cornet in K. <hi>J—s</hi> his Army, that ſhe had always affectionately loved him, with all the Truth and Fidelity of a Wife, till that Adventure upon the Road utterly alienated her Heart from him, conceiving ſuch a natural Averſion to a
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:96167:14"/>to a Coward, (in which to her long deluſion, ſhe had never till then an occaſion of trial of him) that ſhe loath'd the very thought of him. This Declaration was but a new Spur to the Captains Affections, being ſtrangely delighted both with her Perſon and Humour, inſomuch that before they parted, a match was ſtruck up between 'em, that the Lady ſhould leave her Husband, and live with him, who would take care to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain her like a Gentlewoman, ſhe being indeed ſo pleas'd with the Captain, that ſhe was eaſily won to relinquiſh the broken Fortune of a ſlighted Husband, for the Embraces of a Darling Gallant.</p>
            <p>Accordingly, the Captain in a day or two after, (by which time ſhe ſo managed matters at home, as to troop off with all the Bag and Baggage ſhe could make) provided her a Retire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, a Lodging <hi>Alamode;</hi> And accompanied her as often as Affairs would permit, with all the Endearments and Careſſes imaginable. But as Men of his cautious Profeſſion generally make their Reſidences, like Tartar Camps, not long in a place, but always in motion, he danced her about from one quarter of the Town to another, and at laſt a Lodging was fixt for her at one Mr. <hi>Hills</hi> a Turner, his Houſe in a Court at <hi>Hounds-Ditch:</hi> Hither the Captain made his viſits, under the Title of a Brother, his name Captain <hi>Alcock;</hi> For by this time his Fame being loud in the World, and himſelf under the Apprehenſion of too many cloſe Hunters, he made it his ſtudy to croſs the Scent by ſhort turns, and ſmall ſtops; Inſomuch that his viſits here were but once in five or ſix days, and thoſe generally of <hi>Saturdays,</hi> and always at Night Time, not daring to ſtay a whole Night with his dear Miſtreſs, and therefore on purpoſe dignified at this Lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by no higher a Title than a Siſter. The Landlord had ſome time before ſeen and known Captain <hi>Whitney,</hi> but this new name of <hi>Alcock,</hi> and the ſeveral years ago ſince this little know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of his perſon had almoſt defaced that remembrance, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that he went and came without any curioſity or obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from his Landlord, till unfortunately about a week before his apprehenſion the Lady having occaſion to call him back at the Stair Head, upon his departure, inſtead of Brother or <hi>Alcock,</hi> unluckily cried, Mr. <hi>Whitney,</hi> Mr. <hi>Whitney,</hi> one word with you before you go. This being caſually overheard by his Landlord perfectly refreſht his Memory, and recollected his ſleeping know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Captain; and accordingly reſolving to be prepared for his next viſit, and bid fair for the 40 <hi>l.</hi> ſet upon his Head, he
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:96167:14"/>had provided a Conſtable within call, reſolved to ſnap him. But it fell out, as the Miſs 'tis thought had ſome ſmall ſmoking of danger, and therefore had given him ſome cautionary Advice, this laſt Viſit was an extream ſhort one, for before the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable could be fetched, the Captain had taken leave, and ruſht by the juſtled Conſtable; but his Landlord more preſſing and hardy, puſht forward, and boldly grappled him alone himſelf in the Street, in the ſurprize tripping up the Captains Heels; but the Captain recovering himſelf, and getting the Advantage of his weaker Aſſailant, drew his Sword, and backward under his Cloak wounded the Joyner in his Thigh, at which he fell, and a great Out-cry of Stop Thief enſuing, throwing off his Cloak, made a fair pair of Heels for his Life; when unluckily miſtak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his way, inſtead of running down <hi>Bedlam</hi> Lane, he ran through a Hoſiers Shop, where for want of a paſſage through, being ſtopt in the back Room, the whole Body of the Mob ſoon advanced, and our Captain with Sword and Piſtol in hand ſtood at Bay and faced them, till ſuch time Meſſage was ſent both to Major <hi>Richardſon</hi> and the Sheriffs, who approaching with their Reſpective Retinue, Reſiſtance was thought wholly in vain, and the Captain patiently ſurrendred; from whence be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Hand cuft, and put into a Coach, he was uſhered in great Ceremony, (eſpecially if Crouds and Noiſe be any part of State) to <hi>Newgate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this unhappy Durance, though his Leggs were a little tyed, his Name roved far enough; for the whole Town rung at no little rate: His Viſitants were preſently numerous; for where one came under any pretence of charging him with any Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery, a hundred came purely for a ſight of his ſweet Face. To theſe laſt ſort of Gueſts he behaved himſelf with a ſort of a pride and ſtrutt, as if he ſeem'd pleaſed with ſo popular a Vanity as making a Raree-ſhow. To the other ſort that came in as Spies, he deſired 'em to be cautious how they charg'd him with any thing; for it had been a cuſtomary Fallacy amongſt the High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way-men on all occaſions, to own themſelves all to be <hi>Whitneys,</hi> by a trick of ſhewing their left Hands with their Thumbs ſlipt into the palm of their Gloves; whereby very notorious Faults were fathered upon him, of which he was utterly innocent.</p>
            <p>Amongſt his Viſitants one honeſt Countrey-man came to Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peach him of a very Extraordinary Robbery, <hi>viz.</hi> a Maiden-head that the Captain had taken from a young Girl, the Countrey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans Sweet-heart, which was no little heart-breaking to him,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:96167:15"/>as being no mean adorer (if that word be not too high for him) of his dear Laſs thus unhappily debaucht, and worſe than raviſht from him. The Captain was much concern'd at the poor Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey-mans Tears and Sighs on ſo ſorrowful a Subject, and like a Man of Honour utterly abjured ſo much as his leaſt knowledge of the poor Girl ſo traduced and ſlandered, averring her to be a Virgin and a Saint for any thing he knew of her; and in ſhort ſo ſalved her wounded Reputation, and ſo ſweetened the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving good Man into an opinion of her Innocence, that he begg'd a hundred pardons, and immediately troop'd to the very next Gold-ſmiths for a certain Implement call'd a Thumb-Ring, and thence to <hi>Snow-Hill</hi> to the firſt Sales-mans Shop, reſolving to rig himſelf for a Bridegroom immediately, and conſummate before to morrow night; being only heartily afflicted that he could not have the Captain for a Bride-man, unleſs he would make uſe of the <hi>Ordinary</hi> for a Chaplain.</p>
            <p>But to take our leave of his gentler Converſation his kind pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon Viſitants, and bring him before more formidable Faces the Seſſion drew on, and on <hi>Tueſday</hi> the ſeventeenth of <hi>January,</hi> he was brought to the <hi>Old-Bayly</hi> and Indited for a Burglary com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted upon the Houſe of <hi>John Flanders</hi> of <hi>Enfield</hi> in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Mialeſex,</hi> on the 28th of <hi>Auguſt</hi> was twelve month laſt paſt. Here the Evidence, as you have been told at length in the common Seſſions paper, not fully proving the charge upon him, he was Acquited of this firſt Inditctment: But on the morrow on a new charge, for a Robbery committed at <hi>South-Mims waſh,</hi> on the tenth of <hi>November</hi> laſt, he was preſt a little more home, and poſſitively charged with the ſaid Robbery, upon Coviction whereof, he received Sentence of Death.</p>
            <p>After ſuch Serious Circumſtances as the conſideration of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching Death we ought to ſuit our diſcourſe accordingly, nevertheleſs we cannot omit one pleaſant Adventure more. One of his Feminie Votaries was pleaſed to write him this fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Letter,</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:96167:15"/>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>LETTER.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>I Am very ſorry to hear of your Fatal Sentence, but do not preſume ſo brave a valiant Man as your ſelf will fail of Pardon, but if you are in danger, ſend word by the Bearer, and if you think it can be procured, a Party of young Ladies are reſolved to petition Their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties in your behalf; but I am told it cannot be done without taking for better for worſe, and then I am ſure there is a great Objection in the way, being your ſelf al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready in the Matrimonial Nooſe. Now my ſimple Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion is, after Sentence is paſt a Perſon is free, but that's but a Womans imagination, and one that does heartily wiſh it may be ſo. If what I propoſe be poſſible, and you have Courage to venture on the moſt undeſerving of our whole Sex, I'll venture to croſs my Inclination to ſave what I cannot give, for I have ever been averſe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Matrimony, nor do I now do it for the ſake of a Husband, or any other Self-Intereſt; for if I were once aſſured of your dear Life, I deſire no more to ſee you.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>After his peruſal hereof, he borrowed ſome Minutes from his deepeſt Meditations to return this Acknowledging An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>MADAM,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>I Am now at a ſtand how to expreſs my Thanks for your moſt generous Intentions towards me, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not imagine how I have merited two ſuch great Favours as you are pleaſed to mention; firſt to ſave my Life,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:96167:16"/>and then to make that happy by this way you mention. As for the Nooſe you ſpeak of, 'tis eaſier ſlipt, than that I am like to come into, if not prevented by you, having no Aſſurance or Hopes of Life from any body.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>We will not preſume to enquire into the Integrity of this profeſſing kind Lady, or whether her ſelf in the Head of her Female Troop were true to their Aſſignation, in meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at the doleful <hi>Padington</hi> Scene, in their neceſſary ſupplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Virgin Weeds, as the foremention'd charitable ſuppliants for his Deliverance by tying one Nooſe for the ſlipping the other; all we have to aſſure you is that both our Letters are ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batim from the Originals.</p>
            <p>But notwithſtanding the diſmal Voice of Fate; <hi>viz. To the Place of Execution, &amp;c.</hi> the Captain ſo divided the Affections of the People, that the favourable Party had that extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Eſteem for ſomething they were pleas'd to call Bravery in him, that whether from their skill in the Stars that ſome Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nign <hi>Mercurial</hi> Planet ſmil'd upon him, or that they fancied the Court muſt look upon him with Their Eyes, they concluded for certain that a Beam of Royal Mercy would ſhine for his Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance. Inſomuch that his Life and Death, like the Surrender of <hi>Limerick,</hi> was the daily ſubject of very high Wagers. But the high-flown Deliverance-Men received ſome ſmall Mortification when they ſaw him move off up the <hi>High-Holborn</hi> Road, the Right-hand-man of the firſt File, with ſeven others of his Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy Brethren on <hi>Friday</hi> the 27th of <hi>January.</hi> But their drooping Hearts were ſoon enliven'd again. For the Deputy Marſhal by a Reprieve from the Court of <hi>Kings-Bench</hi> poſting towards <hi>Tyburn</hi> in a Coach through <hi>Hide-Park,</hi> attended his Reception there, where the Croud was ſo thick, that he could not poſſibly get up to the Captain but by mounting a Horſe to make his way through the Preſs. The Captain was then dreſt in a fine Silk Night-Gown, a large white Wig, and a white Beaver-Hat; all which perſonal Imbelliſhments more highly attracted a great many favourable, if not ſome wet Eyes, and poſſible more particularly entituled him to that laſt univerſal Civility always paid to his circumſtances; <hi>viz. That every Man's handſome that goes to be hang'd.</hi> But when his Reprieve came, there was no ſmall repeated Shouts amongſt his numerous
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:96167:16"/>Spectators. From thence preſently mounted behind a Rugged<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fac'd Man-catcher of the <hi>Poultrey-Compter,</hi> his particular Friend, and as to the Aſpect much more the Butcher of the two; and under a Detachment of ſome other of the Halbeteers he was with great Joy uſher'd back towards <hi>Newgate;</hi> where by the way, to take a cheering Cup, he was convey'd to the <hi>Fountain</hi> Tavern on <hi>Snow-Hill,</hi> and entertain'd for near two hours to the Tune of Two and twenty ſhillings Reckoning: For which his aforeſaid hard-favour'd <hi>Poultrey-Steward,</hi> at that time being not ſtrong in pocket, for want of the <hi>Rhino,</hi> very kindly dropt his Silver Sword at the Bar, as honourable Guarrantee for the ſaid ſum. During his Entertainment here, the Houſe was ſo throng'd, that the Landlord was forc'd to be at the charge of Watch and Ward to keep his Door; and 'twas no ſmall Ticket could gain Admiſſion. Acceſs being ſo difficult, amongſt the other crouding Viſitants, were four paſſionate Females, being a French Baud, and three of her fair Nurſery, who though they were Miſtreſſes of but little Engliſh, had happily ſo much French Stratagem, that coming all dreſt in white Sarcenet-Hoods, Night-Rails, and white Aprons, they pretended they had been at the Gallows with a deſign to have begg'd his Life, and therefore deſired the honour of coming to the ſpeech of him: So generous a preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion ſoon made their way up to him; but the Captain being al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together a ſtranger to 'em, and truly a little wanting Faith, gave 'em but a ſhort, and not over courteous Reception. However this ſhort-ſnatcht Bleſſing had thoſe tranſporting Effects, that our four white Damſels, with two kind Cullies, their warm Companions, made a <hi>Jubilee</hi> Afternoon on't, the Revel not concluding till paſt Twelve at Night, in which time they made a hard ſhift to ſuck up Thirty ſhillings in good ſoft Sack, in which 'twas obſerved that the dear Captain's often repeated Health made it go ſo glibly down, that in truth they ſtaled as much as they drank.</p>
            <p>But to return to our Captain, this ſhort-liv'd Reprieve was attended by a new Summons to Mortality; <hi>viz.</hi> a new Warrant received on <hi>Sunday</hi> Morning following for his Execution at the May Pole in the <hi>Strand</hi> on <hi>Wedneſday</hi> next the firſt of <hi>February.</hi> Here our Wager Men's Hearts began to beat again; and for a ſuitable Accommodation for his Funeral Gueſts, a great many Scaffolds were accordingly built, and ſeats beſpoken at pretty lumping Prices, in Balconies, Windows, Turrets, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> their
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:96167:17"/>great defeat, by Virtue of a ſecond Warrant not received till late on <hi>Tueſday</hi> night, the Tragick Scene was chang'd to St. <hi>Johns-Street</hi> between <hi>Hicks Hall,</hi> and <hi>Smithfield Bars.</hi> Hither accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly our departing Capt to bid the World adieu, was uſher'd with the uſual Formalities; and poſſibly this laſt Exit Scene was cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen for him, on purpoſe to take his farewel amongſt his own Original Fraternity, the Brothers of the Pole-axe and Cleaver, the <hi>Smithfield Bar</hi> Neighbourhood; and partly as a rebuke to their over inſolent rejoycings at his Reprieve, and over haſty confidence of his Life and Pardon.</p>
            <p>But now to ſhake hands with the Rover, and to take a little Diſcourſe with the Chriſtian at parting. We muſt do his Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory this Right, that not only his whole Behaviour in the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon was all along very Modeſt and Serious; but after his Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence he was ſo ſenſibly toucht with the Thoughts of Death, that he made a conſiderable Preparation for appearing before a Higher Tribunal. 'Tis true he did not think fit in all his peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence to oblige the World with any particular Detection of his Accomplices, or the Arraignment of any other ſins but his own. And at the Place of Execution (where he received the favour of about an hour and a halfs preparation for Eternity) he was extreamly penitent, pray'd heartily for the King, acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his grateful Thanks for his kind five days Reprieve, owning Charity to all Mankind, and dying with all the Symptoms of the moſt fervent Zeal and Devotion.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>Page 18. l. 3. for <hi>Banbury</hi> read <hi>Bury.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
